Okay, we're back to our meditations. Now
remember we're doing an act of truth
meditation.
Okay, and don't forget what that means. We are... in ancient india...
I remember for example, the Buddha
might say something like this...
the Buddha had a half-brother Devadatta
who was very
jealous of him, and i remember
there's a story where he--Devadatta--
gets sick
and Lord Buddha tries to put his hand on
his head to measure his temperature,
and Devadatta is so jealous of the
Buddha that he gets angry and he says,
"Take your hand off me".
"You're trying to hurt me... you're
doing voodoo on me."
And then lord Buddha says, "Look, I wasn't
doing voodoo i was trying to help you."
And Devadatta said, "no no you
weren't trying to help me" and then
Buddha says
"Look, let's do the act of truth thing
okay?" And Devadatta is like "what's
an act of truth?"
And he says, "Look over here is the
Ganges river..."
If you've ever been to the Ganges river
i mean it's unbelievable...
if you're in a train it might take
an hour to cross the ganges on a bridge,
it's unbelievable.
It's a unbelievable huge river, beautiful
river.
And... so buddha says to his
half-brother, "Look, let's do an act of
truth."
"If I was trying to help you and not hurt
you, then may the Ganges river float
backwards right now!" And then the Ganges river will
go...
and then it will start to flow backwards
you know, back to the Himalayas.
Back up to the Himalayas you know, and
i like to think of... we have a big
waterfall here in America
called Niagara Falls. So just imagine
thousands of tons of water going
backwards,
that's called an act of truth. And it's a
tradition in our lineage.In our
tradition it's a tradition
to do an act of truth, so what kind of
act of truth are we going to do here?
We have something going on with the
virus. Of course the virus is hurting
people,
making people sick, killing people.
But aside from the virus, we have a huge
amount of fear
right now, and i don't mean ...
there's rioting in the streets, there was
a little bit, but i don't mean everyone
is like screaming or something like that.
But there's sort of a
a deep silent fear of what's going on. We
don't know how long it's going to be. We
don't know how long it's going to go on for.
We don't know what's going to happen to
our family; to our job.
There's sort of a deep undercurrent of
fear going on in our societies, all of our
societies right now.
So let's try to send that fear
to the middle of the sun. Let's destroy
that fear okay? We're going to do an act of truth
okay? We're going to do an act of truth:
If it's true that during the virus
i tried to comfort one person okay...
I don't know... your mom, or your kids, or
your dog.
My dog was getting nervous. He didn't
know what was going on,
but he was uncomfortable, you could see
he was nervous.
He felt something going on with the humans,
and then i would pet him and give him
some snacks and you know...
try to make him feel better. So in my
case it's true
that during the virus I have done at
least
one small thing to calm
somebody else down, you know? It happened
to be my dog okay?
Because I only had two people in my
house. Me, and veronica, and the dogs
okay?
Veronica doesn't get scared, the dog was
nervous, so I was just trying to help
the dog. So it is true
that i did this one good thing, so i have
the raw material
for an act of truth you know? We've been
calling it the "bullet
in the gun" you know?
Like i have a...
I have some raw materials, so your job
during this meditation
is going to be to do an act of truth;
we are going to shoot a bullet
into the fear that everybody has. We're
going to try to send it to the middle of
the sun.
25 million degrees. Burned up
in the middle of the sun okay?
We're going to try to do that.
And to do that... you're going to have to
remember something you did during the
virus times...
the time of the virus, to help someone
else who was nervous or scared
okay?
And then you're going to do an act of
truth:
"if it's true
that I helped one other person who was
nervous or scared
during this virus, then may the
virus be
killed by my act of truth."
"May i send the
virus to the middle of the sun and destroy it."
Okay?
And I
think it'd be really...
cool, i mean i don't know if we will have
the strength or the wisdom to do it,
but it would be cool if
our if our meditations could stop the
virus.
That would be really
amazing.
i don't know if we're good
enough to do it,
but it would be it's certainly worth a
try right?
It's certainly
something cool to try, so let's try.
And as we go through...
After we identify that good thing you
did,
we're going to send it... to help
different people.
And there's a list of
19 different things that hurt
people okay?
We already took care of the
hell beings.
We covered the animals,
we covered the
pretas--the hungry ghosts.
And now in this meditation we're going
to help out the human beings okay?
We're going to do
something for human beings,
and i think if you listen to the recording that we
did of the dedication chapter,
this is one of
the most beautiful
pieces of spiritual poetry ever.
And
how master shantideva imagines
walking across the planet,
and helping all kinds of different
people with different problems okay?
So let's get started.
Please sit up straight.
Okay, drink something.
I like left hand down, right hand down on
top.
I kind of let my thumbs... I don't try to
do this like the Buddha does
because I get distracted trying to keep them up.
So i just let them fall down.
Sit up super straight.
And let's come to our breath. We're just
going to do 15 minutes, it's not a long
meditation.
Make it a make it a really good 15 minutes.
Let's watch our breath. 10 long exhales.
You can link it to your heartbeat, it's
it's kind of more fun.
Now try to identify sometime during the
last few months--
during the time of the virus--
when you broke out of your shell
of self-concern.
You noticed that someone else was afraid,
and you tried to make them feel better.
You tried to make them feel safer.
Here we go. Don't... and then keep that in
mind, we're going to use it for an act of
truth.
Now let's use that act of truth like a
bullet.
And we transform--
we imagine that we are Manjushri.
We are like this incredibly beautiful
divine Buddha,
and we are walking through the world--
this virus world--
and we are touching people.
First we meet people who are blind,
probably in your life you've known a few
blind people.
And like in the stories of Jesus, we
touch their eyes
and then suddenly they're able to see.
Imagine that.
"If it's true
that i helped a person who was afraid
during the last few months,
then may all the blind people in this
world see see things."
"Right now, in this moment."
"May the Ganges river flow backwards."
"May blind people see."
"May deaf people hear."
"I do an act of truth, if it's true I was
kind to someone who was afraid... if I made
them feel better...
may all the deaf people in this world
hear suddenly." "Hear
all the beautiful sounds of this world
the birds,
music,
loving words of other people."
"If it's true that I helped a person in
the virus times,
by that good karma
may Manjushri appear to every woman
right now who is in labor, who is about
to have a baby,
suffering that extraordinary pain, and
ready to make that final sacrifice
to give life to another being."
"If it's true I tried to help someone,
then may every one of those women have a
very easy easy childbirth--
painless like the Buddha's mother did."
There are people in the world who have
no... they're so poor they don't even have
a shirt, or
they don't have clothes. And i have seen
in my life, in my travels, I've seen these
people.
"And may they suddenly--through my
act of truth--may they have beautiful
soft sturdy clothing
to protect them."
"If it's true that i helped someone in the [time of the] virus, then may all the people in this
world who are hungry,
at this moment they cannot get food,
there's no way they can get food, then
may they
be filled." "May food suddenly come to them
and made they be filled." When I first went
to India...
I saw a man on his hands and knees eating
grass like a
animal.
And so there are people like that, there
is hunger like that,
especially now.
There are many many people in the world
who have lost all their money.
I spoke to some of the monks at the
monastery this morning,
and in India it's happening... there
there are people with no money at all.
They had a little bit... I have met
farm workers in the fields around
the monastery who who have one piece of
bread
and that's all they own. And those people
are
in need of money, may they suddenly have
money.
We all know people who have lost people
they love...
and they are grieving and sometimes
grief takes years, sometimes grief can
take 10 years, 20 years.
So may those people, by my act of truth,
may they suddenly finish with their
grieving. May they find comfort.
There are people who have lost hope. They see no hope for the future.
They don't even want to get out of bed,
they don't talk much,
they don't do much, they sit at home and
they feel despair.
"May I, by my act of truth,
may those people feel hope."
Next in this chapter Shantideva... Master
Shantideva talks about people who are sick,
and of course there are tens of
thousands... hundreds of thousands of
people are sick right now.
"And by my act of truth,
may their sickness finish; may they start
to feel
very comfortable and very healthy."
Next is fear. There are people... of course
there are
millions of people right now in fear.
"And may my act of truth remove that fear."
Virus is
difficult, virus is deadly, but the fear
on top of the virus it's almost worse
than the virus.
Next Master Shantideva says, "let's do
an act of truth
on all those people who have no power in
society". They are un-empowered.
Other people boss them around, other
people tell them what to do.
Most often because of race, or religion,
or beliefs... they are
un-empowered in our society.
And by this act of truth,
may people who for those reasons have
have no authority or no power in this
society, may they suddenly
come to full power.
Even in the time of the virus there
are
countless people on the road, flying...
still some airplanes are going.
More and more people are driving; people
are trying to get home. People in India
are walking home,
for a thousand miles to get home
during the virus. May each person
who is on the way home---may my
act of truth---may my good karma help them on their way. May they have a smooth
trip, and an easy trip.
Then there are countless people who they are not traveling because they have
nowhere  to go...
they don't have a home, they don't have
relatives, they don't have a family.
There's nowhere they can go for help.
And i do my act of truth for them.
I do my act of truth for children, small
children.
They are especially vulnerable. People
take advantage of them, people hurt them,
people ignore them, people don't take
care of them...
and by this act of truth may all
children...
may all young children in this world be
protected,
and happy, and have a beautiful childhood.
The elderly are very similar to the
children.
They are... they used to be strong, they
used to be like you and me,
and their only sin is that they got old
and they don't have the energy to work,
to make money anymore. They don't have
the energy to do the
little day-to-day things they used to do
in their home; they can't cook anymore,
they can't make the bed anymore, they
can't walk to the toilet anymore.
Like small children, they are very
vulnerable.
And may my act of truth make them strong and protected.
Three more and then we're done with the
meditation.
And it's so beautiful that Shantideva
identifies the really major problems of
this world. He says there are
millions of people who had trouble
sleeping last night,
maybe you have this problem. I know I
have it sometimes.
And we just can't sleep, we wake up in
the middle of the night, we stare
at in the darkness and we worry.
So may... through this act of truth,
may all people who have trouble sleeping,
may they sleep well tonight.
People who are mentally
troubled. They're mentally
broken. There's a lot of, for example in
America, a lot of veterans
of fighting--ex-soldiers--
who have this problem, and their minds
are troubled; they're not quite normal.
I do an act of truth for you.
And then finally says Shantideva, there
are people who are just
completely crazy. They are locked up
in a hospital, they are given heavy drugs,
they are wasting away, locked up in a
room.
I had a friend whose relative got Covid
and died from it.
And the irony is she was already locked
up,
in a mental asylum for over 30 years,
and then inside there she dies from this
virus.
So i also pray for these people.
I send my act of truth to them
as if i were Manjushri.
Let's come back to our breath. Three deep
breaths, three deep exhales.
And slowly open your eyes. Take a stretch.
I like to take a stretch.
We're going to do five meditations total,
and that's the second one. And please do
it this week, try to do it once or twice
a day.
It's very short and it's very beautiful.
See you for the next one.